Russian-Japanese War the Japanese, they are like
русско-японская война японцы они как
the Slavs, too, as I understand it, they fought hard
славяне тоже я так понимаю сильно бились
and
и
won Hello Hello, I’m
выиграли Здравствуйте Здравствуйте я из
from the city of Khmelnitsky Where are you from? I’m from the city of
города Хмельницкий Вы откуда Я из города
Novosibir, it looks like what you’re talking about is funny,
Новосибир схо чтом беседуете прикольно
I’m talking about
общаюсь так о
the war, war, history, politics, I’m also
войне война история политика тоже
discussing it, I understand, look, you saw
обсуждаю понял вот смотрите Вы видели
the news that today the Ukrainian  water
новость что сегодня украинские водные
drones destroyed a Russian ship, I
дроны уничтожили корабль российский
heard a
слышал
video there, just Well, ours are
там видео просто Ну наши же
rising in the layout and in a thermal imager,
выкладкой поднимается и в тепловизоре
in short, probably in  battle set hit yes
короче наверно в боя комплект попали да
yes They just hit the same
да Они так именно раз ударили в то же
point once and the same and the fourth
точку и в ту же и четвёртый да Третий в
yes The third one in the same Well well done fellows are not so
туже Ну молодцы молодцы не такие
useless yes Question How is it
бесполезны да Вопрос Как так получается
that in the second year its Yes Ukraine
что на втором году сво Да Украина
continues to destroy the Black Sea Fleet
продолжает уничтожать Черноморский флот
beats the
лупит
Nizhny Novgorod
обла Нижегородскую
region  Ukrainians, after all, the
область украинцы вс-таки
Slavs know how to fight, adapt
славяне умеют воевать приспосабливаться
Well done, and not the Slavs don’t know how, the Mongols don’t
Молодцы а не славяне не умеют монголы не
know how to fight Yes, for example, it’s simple. As
умеют воевать Да например просто Как
practice shows, Europeans  they give up
показывает практика европейцы сдаются
earlier they are supposed to have it as if they don’t have
раньше положено у них как будто нет
the rods they held it as if that is,
стержни держать держал как будто То есть
for example, are the Poles Europeans or
например а поляки они европейцы или
Slavs? They are holy, that is, the Poles don’t
славяне Они свя то есть поляки не
give up like
сдаются как
Europe, they ate there too. Well done. I understand,
Европе ели там тоже Молодцы Поня понял
yes, I understood correctly what happens.
да то я правильно понял что получается
Everything that comes next is Poland there, Germany.
Всё что дальше Польша там Германия
France Italy they don’t seem to have them anymore
Франция Италия они уже типа нет у них
Darling
Душка
Yes, it’s difficult to say so, but from what
Да сложно так сказать но из того что
world practice shows, it seems like
показывает мировая практика как будто бы
no, that is, well, in world practice Yes,
нет то есть ну в мировой практике Да
there are such myths there, for example, like
есть такие мифы там там например как
King Leonidas and  300 Spartans
король Леонид да и 300 спартанцев
surrendered quickly, yes And about the Roman army
сдались быстро да А про Римское войско
in general, they surrendered Every time when they
вообще оно сдалось Каждый раз когда
got somewhere, in principle, yes, the Europeans were
куда-то попадало в принципе да европейца
wrong. I didn’t say I didn’t say gi ehi there, the
не так Я же не говор Я же нею ги эхи там
Armed Forces were different, I understood. It’s interesting
ВС было подругому понял А интересно
when we say let’s do this. The Third Reich
когда вот наме давайте так Третий рейх
surrendered
сдавался
quickly  The Third Reich is just an
быстро Третий рейх это как раз таки
exception for very obvious reasons, and
исключение по очень понятным причинам а
they were Slavs, they were
они славяне были это были первые
probably the first Europeans who were very
наверное европейцы которые были очень
strictly charged with ideology
жёстко заряжены идеологией
so so interesting In short, I’m talking about VM, everything so
так так интересно Короче я по ВМ все
far is that I’ve read many conflicts,
пока то что я читал многие конфликты
wars are different, but for example, well, of course,
войны различные но например ну понятно
I don’t take the Ukrainians at all, they were in the
украинцев я вообще не беру они были в
Russian Empire, there
Российской империи
were all the wars there of the Russian Kingdom of the
все были войны там Русского царства
Russian
Российской
Empire Well, it’s
империи Ну там
straight out What books have you read, what’s there about
пря Какие книжки вы читали что там про
the bad ones  Europeans in Wars, well, tell
плохих европейцев в Войнах ну расскажите
me, I’m interested in what kind of wars these are not
мне интересно про какие войны это не
books, I just know the conflicts
книжки это я просто ну знаю конфликты
there, what kind of conflicts What kind of conflicts are
там раз какие конфликты Какие конфликты
there? The Napoleonic Wars are there, yes What What stop stop stop what in  In the Napoleonic Wars, it
стоп стоп что в наполеоновских Войнах
was not so with the Europeans, the French
было не так с европейцами французы
went through all of Europe and were stuck only with
прошли всю Европу и застряли только у
us, wait, wait Stop who fought
нас подождите подождите Стоп кто воевал
in the Napoleonic
в наполеоновских
Wars, well, all of Europe is practically
Войнах ну вся Европа практически
Western, all of Europe fought, but they are
Западная ев вся Европа воевала но они
weaklings Well, they just gave up very
слабаки Ну они просто сдавались очень
quickly, unlike the
быстро в отличие от
Russians So, tell me  uh, can you
русских Так а ну расскажите ээ можете
tell me? Here in the Napoleonic Wars
мне сказать Вот в наполеоновских Войнах
Yes, uh, the heroic defense of Moscow
Да ээ героическая оборона Москвы
by the Russians from  Napoleon, you can tell
русскими от Наполеона можете рассказать
this episode,
этот эпизод
and there was a heroic battle at Borodino,
а была героическая битва при бородином
there it would be later, this is only later,
там бы Это уже потом это уже потом вот
look how tell how the Russians did not
смотри как скажите как русские не
surrender in Moscow How the Russians did not surrender
сдались в Москве Как русские не сдали
Moscow to Napoleon, you can tell me
наполеону Москву можете рассказать мне
this, we didn’t surrender from Moscow, we just
это мы из Москвы не сдавались мы просто
retreated,
отступили
ran away, left the city  for
убежали оставили город на
looting, well, you can’t say that
разграбление не Ну нельзя же сказать что
they ran away from Bakhnu, too, just tact,
убежали из бахну тоже такти просто сри
that is, look, that is, you just
то есть смотри То есть ты только что
admitted that  Russians Yes, they didn’t stand for
признал что россияне Да не стояли за
Moscow,
Москву
after all, they are
всё-таки они
weak and strategy You have to win
слабачка и стратегия Ты должен победить
strategically tactically you can
стратегически тактически ты можешь
make many unpopular decisions But
делать многие непопулярные решения Но
strategically you have to calculate everything
стратегически ты должен всё рассчитать
so as to win so that’s what we’ll
так чтобы победить так вот мы так и
do
сделаю
Yeah Got it Tell me what the Russians did
Угу Понял Расскажите как русские сделали
in the First World War
в Первую мировую войну
they did  well, how did they do it, for example,
сделали что ну как они сделали например
that is, as I understand it, the Russians
то есть я так понимаю что русские же
lost the First World War. Yes, in the First
проиграли Первую мировую Да в первою
World War, we concluded an agreement with the
мировую войну Мы заключили договор с
Germans, it’s called the Brest Treaty, the
немцами называется Брестский бре
Lithuanian Treaty, that’s right,
литовский правильно
its ladies  concluded because they
дамы его заключили потому что
lost on German terms
проиграли на немецких условиях
for a treaty on German terms, it’s clear
за договор о немецких условиях понятно
yes I explain In bre wait in this in this
да Объясняю В в бре подожди в это в этом
agreement what was Ukraine was recognized as an
договоре что было Украина признавалась
independent
независимым
state As far as I remember Yes it
государством Насколько помню Да
was recognized yes That is, you lost to
признавалась да То есть вы проиграли
Germany and Germany on its own terms Yes
Германии и Германия на своих условиях Да
it stood  for example, what did they admit? That is,
она стояла например что признали То есть
you lost Yes, yes, yes, that’s right.
вы проиграли Да да да да всё верно Это
Now I’ll explain why this happened, this
объясняю теперь почему это произошло это
happened because we were in the midst of a
произошло потому что у нас в разгаре шла
civil war. You just can’t
гражданская война Просто нельзя ть это
watch this. This is no one else  not interested There are
смотри Это уже никого не интересует Есть
tactics and strategy, you know, the Germans Yes, the
тактика и стратегия понимаешь немцы Да
Germans just tactically made a
немцы просто тактически сделали вам
civil war for you, well, look at this, you
гражданскую войну ну смотрите это ж вы
know this story of how the Germans sent
знаете эту историю как немцы прислали
you revolutionaries, really, you can
вам революционеров правда можно так
say so Yes, there is such a version Yes, the Germans
сказать Да есть такая версия Да немцы
beat you tactically and strategically,
вас обыграли тактически и стратегически
that is, what have you got there  It was going on
то есть что у вас там шло Это уже никого
No one cares anymore You signed a shameful
не интересует вы подписали позорный
peace treaty Yes I
мирный договор Да
lost I agree It’s interesting Yes the
проиграл согласен интересненько да
Russian-Japanese can’t So I
русско-японская на можете Вот я так
understand that the Russian-Japanese war The Japanese
понимаю что русско-японская война японцы
are like the Slavs too  As I understand it, they
они как славяне тоже я так понимаю
fought hard and won. More precisely, they didn’t
сильно бились и выиграли Точнее не
win, but Russia lost the
выиграли а Россия с позором проиграла
Russo-Japanese War in disgrace,
русско-японскую войну
so no, not in disgrace, there were
так там нет там не с позором там были
long negotiations, but the Japanese demanded
переговоры долгие вот японцы требовали
one thing in the negotiations, but didn’t get it,
одно по переговорам но не получили этого
and Well, they won anyway, and part of
и Ну всё равно они победили и часть
Sakhalin is there  some lands they are, that
Сахалина там какие-то земли они да то
is, in the Russo-Japanese War 95
есть в русско-японской войне 95
Russia lost not to the Slavs but to the Japanese.
Россия проиграла не славянам а японцам
It’s interesting, but in the Crimean War you can
Интересно а в Крымской войне можете
say who
сказать кто
won almost all of them  In the Crimean Wars Well,
победил почти во всех Крымских Войнах Ну
in general,
Войнах вообще
with these Turks, we won the wars, not
с этими с турками мы побеждали кро не
the pro-turks, but some French,
протур вот какие-то там французы
some British, some non-Slavs there in
англичане какие-то не славяне там
Europe, and there was no
Европе там тоже причём не было
defeat, there were treaties,
поражение были договоры оден
this can be regarded as a
это можно это можно расценить да как
defeat, because we are not there  you achieved
поражение потому что мы там не добились
your goal too, and it’s not that you didn’t achieve it,
своего тоже да и не то что не добились
you lost
вы потеряли
yours Yes, yes, that is, look, I
свою Да да да то есть смотри я правильно
understood correctly Look, I immediately Yes, I found it when the
понял Смотри я сходу Да нашёл когда
French and British were pushing the Russians
французы и англичане надавали русским
the Japanese pushed the Slavs in the Crimean War to the Slavs in the Crimea in the Russo-Japanese War Yes, these Germans pushed in the First World War, it turns out the Russians Damn, something in short is not going well with the Russians Maybe when And I realized maybe once in the time of Napoleon there were Slavs in Rus' who there, well, you see what’s the matter when there was a Japanese war, essentially we didn’t only fight with Japan because it was Western countries that actively helped them there  this time,
помогали именно западные страны это раз
in the war of which you said the Crimean,
а в войне которой вы сказали крымскую
the British and French even
англичане и французы войсками даже
fought against us with troops, so about the Lower Slavs and
воевали против нас так о Нижне славяне а
Not a weakling,
Не слабачка
well, excuse me, they extinguished the crowd, I even understood, I
ну извините меня толпой гасят даже
understood. Can you
понял понял А можете
tell me with whom in the crowd you extinguished
сказать с кем в толпе вы гасили
Napoleon? We were in an alliance with the British from
Наполеона Мы были в союзе с англичанами
Prussia  that is, in the crowd you see you and the crowd
пруса то есть в толпе видите вы с толпе
brought down Lev, really No, not really
валили Льва правда Нет не совсем так
because, well, in Russia we fought
потому что ну при в России мы воевали
only with Russians, that is, we need to do it again
только русскими то есть нам ещё раз ещё
look, the coalition was against
раз смотри коалиция была против
Napoleon Yes, of course And they fought on different
Наполеона Да конечно И воевали на разных
sides, yes That is, you didn’t You
сторонах да То есть вы не Сами вы не
yourself didn’t fight your own You weren’t there, but in the
сами воевали сво Вы же не были там вот в
battle of Tirlo there were Russian
битве под терло были русские
troops at Waterlow No, I also think that
войска при ватерлоу Нет я тоже думаю что
no, really not Yes, that’s according  in essence there was already a
нет правда не Да ну это по сути уже была
desperate
Отчаянная
attempt
попытка
to grab onto the ground, let's say Napoleon
ухватиться за землю скажем так Наполеона
was no longer the same he was no longer the same Yes,
он уже был не тот он уже был не тот Да
Napoleon was no longer the same yes Or maybe
Наполеон уже был не тот да А может Вот
Look, let me see what  When Russia
смотри давайте я смотрю что Когда Россия
was not in a coalition with Western countries
была не в коалиции с западными странами
Yes, it was very good, like in the
Да она очень хорошо от вот как в
Russo-Japanese War Yes, like in the First
русско-японской войне Да как в Первой
World War Yes, no, I wouldn’t say that No, it
Мировой Да нет я бы так не сказал Нет
just happened that
просто так сложилось что против нас
these countries united against us And you can, yes
объединялись э страны А може можете да
you can say when  what kind of
можете сказать когда вы какую вы
war did you win on your own,
победили самостоятельно войну
on
самостоятельно
your own, on your own, no, well, in principle, you can
самостоятельно Не ну в принципе можно
say in the Second World War, we defeated the
сказать во второй мировой мы победили
Germans on our own, not on our own,
немцев самостоятельно вообще не самостоя
which Germans, on your own, are you kidding me?
каких немцев самостоятельно что
Well, the Second Front was opened in
Ну Второй фронт был открыт в сорок
1944 once again  look
четвёртом году ещё раз ещё раз смотри ты
now, in all seriousness, when the Germans
сейчас на полном серьёзе когда немцы
fought Since 1939, yes And you
воевали С тридцать девятого года да А вы
entered the war in 1941 Yes, you are
вступили в войну в сорок первом Да ты
now saying in all seriousness that you were the
сейчас на полном серьёзе говоришь что вы
only ones who defeated the
единственные побороли
Germans, practically the only ones, that is,
немцев практически единственные то есть
come on, England didn’t fight
давай так Англия не боролась с
Germany, practically no, the United States didn’t
Германией практически нет США не
fight  I say forty whose year they began
боролась я говорю соро чей год начали
to open the second In short, all these British
открыли второй Короче все эти британские
colonies did not fight there England Oh, this is
колонии не боролись там Англия Ой это
Zealand, rub the number of troops on
Зеландия потрите количество войск на
Africans with whom then on  On the African
африканс по с кем тогда на африканском
front, Hitler fought with the Soviet
фронте воевал Гитлер с советским
Union, the British, so it means that after all, there
союзом англичане так то значит всё-таки
was a coalition at war. Well, you are a little.
воевала была коалиция Ну вы вы маленько
Open it up,
Это Откройте
read the number of troops
пею почитайте количество войск которы
there literally was probably 5%, or
там там буквально было наверно 5% или а
that is, it turns out only Everything I understood the
то есть получается только Всё я понял
British. In short, look, So how much
англичан Короче вот смотри Так сколько
states were part of the anti-Hitler
государств входило в антигитлеровскую
coalition,
коалицию
I don’t know the number, created in
я количество не знаю создана в сорок
1942 Yes, like
втором году Да Типа
it’s not that they de facto
она не то что они де-факто деюра
declared war, but de facto  they didn’t fight, these are
объявили войну а де-факто не воевали это
different things No wait, well, as
разные вещи Нет подожди ну как сказал
Churchill said Well, Fulton’s speech from his speech
Черчиль Ну фултонской речи из его речи
More precisely, we can conclude that he wanted to
Точнее можно сделать вывод что он хотел
defeat communism with the hands of the Germans, that’s
руками немцев победить коммунизм вот и
all, I’m looking at the map Yes, uh, of the
всё я смотрю карта Да ээ
countries of the anti-Hitler coalition,
стран антигитлеровской коалиции вот
Wikipedia is stupid there In short, everything
Википедии там тупо Короче всё
is green
зелёненькое
Except for those who Well  for Germany there
Кроме тех кто Ну за Германию
were really very few countries, there were
реально мало-мало стран было страны
Axis countries, almost the whole world, it was the
оси почти весь мир это была
Anti-Hitler
Антигитлеровская
coalition. Well, on paper it can be whatever you want,
коалиция Ну она на бумаге может угодно
don’t tell the bass  on paper not on
быть не рассказывай бас на бумаге не на
paper everything come on Tell me at least one
бумаге всё давай Скажи мне хоть одну
war that you won without a coalition with
войну которую вы выиграли без коалиции с
others so that you don’t beat someone in a crowd there are
другими чтобы вы не толпой били кого-то
a lot of wars there I don’t even know Well, a lot
куча войн там я даже не знаю Ну куча
tell me Tell me those Tatars fought with the Tatars
скажи Скажи с татарами воевали та татары
how many of those Tatars there are in general like what
сколько там тех татар вообще типа какую
you won a serious war against a serious enemy,
вы серьёзную войну серьёзным противником
like against the Japanese from
выиграли типа против вот от японцев от
rowing from the French and the British in the
гребли от французов с англичанами в
Crimean War from rowing from whom you
Крымской войне от гребли у кого вы
won Well, the Swedes are the Swedes  come, Swedes,
выиграли Ну шведы шведы подойди шведы
where is the
где
Northern War? Well, what kind of war is Peter I? Yes, the
Северная война Ну какая война Пётр I Да
war was fought.
сражался война
What is the name of the Northern War? Northern
Какая называется Северная война Северная
War Let’s look now, like that’s what it’s
война Давайте смотрим сейчас вроде так
called if I’m not you,
называется если я не ю
yes, look at the Northern War. The Great
да вот смотрите Северная война Великая
Twenty Years’ War, the war that lasted
вот двадцатилетняя война война длившаяся
between the Swedish kingdom and the coalition of
между шведским королевством и коалицией
Northern European states, Saxony,
государств Северной Европы саксония
Russian  kingdom and the Norwegian
русское царство да норвежское
kingdom of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth That is, you
королевство реч посполитая То есть вы
defeated Charles, not Peter I, but a
победили Карла не Пётр I а победила
coalition of European
коалиция европейских
[music]
[музыка]
states of large
государств крупных
states won, you understand  when there are wars
государств вы поймите когда идут войны
of any kind there is always interest go Wait
любые всегда есть интереса поди Подожди
Stop stop stop again you are in the
Стоп стоп стоп ещё раз ты ты в
Russian-Japanese you well they beat us there
русско-японской ты ну нас били там
together that’s why there was a lion in the crowd So
вместе поэтому там и льва толпой Так вы
that’s where you won you were just in the
вот где вы выигрывали вы были как раз в
crowd of civilized strong countries you didn’t
толпе цивилизованных сильных стран не вы
defeat Charles  Yes, it wasn’t you who defeated Sweden,
победили Карла да не вы швецию победили
look, but the coalition won, in reality there
смотри а победила коалиция реально там
were still a lot of enemies of Sweden around Sweden.
вокруг Швеции куча ещё было врагов
Yes, who fought against it, so
Швеции Да которые боролись с ней так вот
tell me at least one war that
на назовите мне хоть одну войну которую
you didn’t win  as part of a coalition and themselves
вы выиграли не в составе коалиции а сами
That's how now I'll try again to simply
Вот как сейчас я попробую ещё раз просто
explain. It's just that maybe you don't understand
объяснить Просто может вы не понимаете
something, look at any war that's
чего-то смотрите любая война которая
been going on there for the last 400 years of war,
идёт последние там 400 лет войны все
they're all not one country against one country,
они нет одной страны против одной страны
you know, there are always some
понимаете всегда есть какие-то
interested parties who help there  this
интересант которые помогают там этой
side or this Therefore, in Wikipedia Where do
стороне или этой Поэтому в Википедии Где
you get the information, apparently there will
вы берёте видимо информацию всегда
always be someone written Who is on this
всегда будет кто-то написан Кто в этой
side then I don’t understand why you are
стороне тог тогда я не понимаю почему вы
offended then that in the Russian-Japanese
тогда обижаетесь что в русско-японской
war they were still there for the Japanese  someone, well,
войне за японцев были там ещё кто-то ну
because we were alone, it’s just that Usually
потому что мы были одни просто Обычно
when there is a War, there is
когда идёт Война есть
this But in this case, we were
это Но в данном случае мы были одни
completely alone and the Japanese,
совсем а японцы
no, you know, seriously,
нет понимаете серьёзно
yes Let’s look like this, not nif Look, we were
да Давайте посмотрим так не ниф Смотри
n’t
не
alone for Japan, there was the British Empire,
одни за Японию была британская Империя
for Russia, there was the Principality of Montenegro, the
за Россию было княжество Черногорие
Principality of
княжество
Bulgaria  not the only ones who have already been in
Болгария не одни уже были уже в
prison, any conflict will open Well, look
колии любой конфликт откроется Ну смотри
I open Yes I really Yes I look, that
Я открываю Да я реально Да смотрю то
is, I really look at the thing I for example
есть реально смотрю на вещь Я например
don’t know I open Yes indeed That
не знаю Я открываю Да действительно То
is, it turns out  the coalition of the Japanese and the
есть получается коалиция японцев с
British gave
британцами дали
you Well, look, you won’t learn anything like this,
вам Ну смотрите вы так ничему не
you will always
научитесь вы всегда когда будете
open it, don’t don’t teach me, I
открывать не не надо меня учить я всё
know everything, there will always be some
знаю деюра всегда будет какие-то
interesting things, come on, let’s
интересант прип Вот давай давайте
talk about the action and talk about what is
давайте про дею и говорить то что
captured on paper, it makes
запечатлено на бумагу
no sense  listen dejura dejura there the French
бы смысла нет слушайте деюра деюра там с
fought with the Germans,
немцами сражались
who surrendered literally
французы которые сдались буквально
almost instantly, and not only did they
практически мгновенно и причём не только
surrender, but more Frenchmen died
сдались а больше французов погибло
defending Hitler’s regime than in the fight  with
защищая режим Гитлера чем в борьбе с
Hitler It’s interesting, but they are recorded how
Гитлером Интересно а они записаны как
they fought like this, like this. Do you understand
они воевали так так так Понимаете в
what? Well, I just explained. Well, somehow
чём Ну я же только что объяснил Ну както
about defending Hitler while defending Hitler. And where did they
об защ Гитлера защищая Гитлера А где они
defend Hitler? That’s just Stack at the
защищали Гитлера Вот как раз Стак в
end, literally before the complete
конце буквально перед сдачей полной
surrender, they defended the French regiment and
капитуляции обороняли французский полк и
someone-  then from the Balts how many
кто-то из прибалтов сколько там
French died there Well Google hundreds of thousands
французов погибло Ну Погугли сотни тысяч
were behind near the Reichstag hundreds of
были за возле рейхстага погибло сотни
thousands died in the total thief of the rest Yam
тысяч в сумме воре реста Ям
understood in short look uh I’m like that  I realized that
понял короче смотрите ээ Я так понял что
we unwound yours very beautifully. This is
мы очень красиво размотали ваше Вот это
Slavic Greatness. Yes, it turned out that, uh,
Славянское Величие Да оказалось что ээ
you Yes, really, from non-Slavs, just
вы Да реально от у не славян просто
in short, don’t worry like your mother. Yes, it turned out that
короче аж как мама не горюй Да оказалось
this was because Yes, they were in
что это потому что Да они были в
coalitions. Yes, but it turns out that
коалициях Да но оказывается что
you only won in
выигрывали Вы только в
coalitions. Well  you are serious with serious
коалициях Ну вам серьёзными с серьёзными
developed states, you can’t
государствами развитыми вас уже не
be processed anymore, you can’t be more accurately washed normally,
обработать не промыть точнее нормально
you are not a
меня вы вы не
promoter of this Yes, it didn’t win in an alliance with
промоера сия Да победила не в союзе с
developed These are other
развитыми Вот такими другими
states Yeah, developed Yes  developed
государствами Угу развитыми Да развитыми
yes Well, I, in principle, understood what you want to
да Ну я я в принципе понял что вы хотите
say. Let’s go to the next one, what,
сказать Давайте следующую что что
what, well, you came up with something for yourself
что ну вы сами себе что-то там придумали
and you believe in it. So I want to
и и в это верите ра Так что я хочу
say, well, voice
сказать Ну озвучьте
it out, well, I understand everything, but you think,
это ну я я всё понял но вы считаете вот
look  you look, I Well, I explained for the
смотрите вы смотрите я Ну я объяснил
third time, I’ll say okay, you just opened
третий раз скажу ладно вы сейчас открыли
Wikipedia and look, they fought for this side
Википедию и смотрите вот за эту сторону
And for this side Yes, I’m looking at the facts,
воевали И за эту сторону Да я факта
and I just explained to you using the example of the French
смотрю вот а я вам на примере французов
that the French
сейчас объяснил что французы они
recorded how they fought and what they fought against
записаны как боролись что против Гитлера
They fought Hitler But in fact, the French
боролись Но на самом деле французы
fought more against the Soviet Union,
больше боролись против Советского Союза
you don’t want to understand this, apparently or what’s
вы это не хотите понять видимо или что
good, how much Let’s So how many
хорошо сколько Давайте Так сколько
French died in the fight against the Soviet
французов погибло в борьбе с советским
Union and how many French died in the
союзом а сколько французов погибло в
fight against Hitler But this is
борьбе с Гитлером А вот вот это это то
what you need to google  You’re not the one
что вам надо погуглить не вы выж вы ж
answering Well, tell me, I’ll explain, look,
отвечаете Ну скажите объясняю смотрите с
in the battle against the anti-Hitler coalition, the
в битве против антигитлеровской коалиции
French died more, this is hundreds of
французов погибло больше это на сотни
thousands, this count, and who died in the
тысяч этот счёт а которые погибли в
fight against the Germans, tens of thousands, I understand where
борьбе с немцами десятки тысяч понял где
this is  You can
такую информацию можем можете мне
also show me information on Wikipedia I
показать также Википедии я Википедии
looked at Wikipedia Let's where Which article should I
смотрел Давайте где Какую статью
look at Wikipedia Tell me I don't know I don't
посмотреть Википедию Скажите Не знаю не
know I don't know Well, you look here
знаю не знаю Ну вы смотре вот Возьмите
Take Now take and find this article and
Сейчас возьмите и найдите эту статью и
tell me I'll look Well, okay, I'll
скажите я посмотрю Ну ладно я сейчас
ruin it right now, I'll ruin it too  It’s
прямо тогда загублю я ж тоже Мне аж
interesting that with the French this is a very
интересно что с французами это очень
interesting version.
интересная версия
So let’s see
Да так давайте посмотрим
[music]
[музыка]
France
600.000 у Франции
lost 600,000. China lost 35 million in total from Japan
потери Китай в ходе из Японии вообще 35
.
а
150,000 died who fought on the
150.000 погибло которые воевали на
side of Hitler and 100,000
стороне Гитлера а 100.000
who were against Hitler That is, only 250
которые против Гитлера То есть всего 250
Yes,
Да
now, well, from what I see Yes, well, this is a
сейчас ну из того что я вижу Да ну тут
very long
очень длинная
article, I The thing is that I’m looking
статья я Дело в том что я вот смотрю
now, here’s the first thing, I went on a spree of sweat in
сейчас вот первое я загули поте цуз во
World War II, the first  here on the
Второй мировой войне первое вот тут на
website of the Ministry of Defense of the Russian
сайте Министерства обороны Российской
Federation Yes writes irretrievable human
Федерации Да пишет безвозвратные людские
losses in the main countries of the
потери в основных странах
anti-Hitler coalition began in the USA
антигитлеровской коалиции стали в США
405,000 in Great Britain 375 in France
405.000 в Великобритании 375 во Франции
600,000 people, that is, France, as
600.000 человек то есть Франция ээ в
part of the anti-Hitler coalition,
составе антигитлеровской коалиции
lost 600,000 people, according to
потеряло 600.000 человек по данным
your Ministry, yes, this is together with
вашего Министерства это да это вместе с
civilians. And I
мирными жителями А я военнослужащих
read military personnel, 250,000 died,
читал военнослужащих погибло 250.000
150 who fought for Hitler and 100 of
150 которые воевали за Гитлера и 100
whom we are now again with  something you have, by the
которые сейчас мы ещё раз с что-то у вас
way I doubt that it’s against
какие-то Я кстати сомневаюсь что против
Hitler  another 100,000
Гитлера ещё 100.000 погибло
military personnel died, but maybe this is another
военнослужащих та может быть это ещ
drawn figure. I think it’s there. I
нарисованная цифра Мне кажется там Я
read somewhere before that there are several
где-то раньше читал что там несколько
tens of thousands, but here as many as 100 are drawn
десятков тысяч по здесь целых 100 нарисо
seriously. Well, maybe add the
серьёзно Ну может быть приплюсовать
Jews, what kind of army did
евреев какая армия была у этого у
France have, so the
Франции так
army now I’m really interested  these are
армия сейчас мне ж прямо интересно это
some kind of fairy tales you are And where did you
какие-то сказки вы такие А где вы это
read this that died in which article
прочитали что погибло вот в какой статье
can you tell me
можете мне
the skarn is called the article is called and
скарн называется статья называется а
let’s calculate how p stop p you
посчитаем как п стоп п вы Википедию
some kind of Wikipedia  Well, officially, or have you found
какую-то Ну официально или вы нашли
some kind of leftist site, the first article is the
какой-то левый сайт первая статья вот
very first one that I found, let's
самая первая которая нашл давайте
give some more official
давайте какой-то более официальные
sources, at least check some
источники хотя бы ну провери какой-то
leftist one.
левый
Sai can’t be called an official
Сай нельзя назвать официальным
source and with all due
источником и всем
respect, I don’t see Wikipedia on Wikipedia, no,
уважению Википеди не вижу Википедии нени
no, the site that has  you are there, I’m
нени сайте который у вас есть мне ж
interested, maybe really, now I
интересно может действительно я сейчас
always thought that the French were [ __ ] fighting,
всегда думал что французы блин боролись
in short, it turns out they were [ __ ] defending the
короче оказывается они блин а защищали
rest of the [ __ ] 100,000 French, like
реста бля 100.000 французов типа
defending the Ukrainians, by the way, they also loved  The
защищали украинцы кстати тоже любили
Russians loved to defend Hitler so much, you
Гитлера защищать русские так любили вот
know, the Vlasov army was oh ro Kaza
знаете армия власовцев была ой ро каза
Kaza Cossacks on the Kuban in short and damn
каза казаки на кубане короче и блин
Skins all sorts of Krasnov
Шкуро всякие там красновы процентном
percentages you are over I don’t know, look
соотношении вы пере Я не знаю смотрите
if we take how many millions of
если мы возьмём сколько миллионов
Russians fought It’s just tough, just
русских воевало Это просто жесть просто
tough Well, let’s Find out about the French
жесть Ну давайте Найдите про французов
so that  here I am Nabu, you know
чтобы вот я Набу знаете
[laughter]
[смех]
Sabu and Sai, we didn’t take information Well
Сабу ещ Сай мы не брали информацию Ну
then,
тогда
here’s some kind of forum where everyone writes
вот какой-то форум там где все пишут Да
What?  whatever Well, here’s a big article Well, well,
что угодно Ну тут статья большая Ну да
that is, look, anyone can just publish
ну то есть смотри любой может выйти
something like an article Here’s what Georgy Zotov wrote
что-то статьи Вот написано Георгий Зотов
and what
и что
was published in the newspaper Argumenty i Fakty
опубликовано в газете Аргументы и Факты
And that’s it, Georgy Zotov wrote in the newspaper
А всё ну Георгий Зотов написал в газете
Argumenty i Fakty And someone republished
Аргументы и Факты А кто-то перепечатала
it on the website  Pikabu Okay Let's find
это на сайт Пикабу О'кей Давайте на
something normal Let's find
нормальном каком-то Давайте найдём в
something real because the Second
каком-то реально потому что Вторая
World War is not some
мировая война - это не какой-то
small conflict, everything has been officially written about it for a long time
маленький конфликт про неё уже давно всё
there are books, scientific
официально написано там книги научные
works, that's where we can really
работы вот где мы что-то можем реально
see something, here's Wikipedia, if there is, yes, there are
увидеть вот Википедия если есть да там
always links to some scientific
есть всегда ссылочки на какой-то научную
Rata Yes, that one said that, or to some
Рату Да тот сказал тот или на какие-то
facts, I see, if yes, if there is
факты я видите я если да вот если ссылки
no link to Wikipedia, then this  it’s an invention of the one who
нет Википедии то это выдумка того кто
wrote this article, that’s why I do
написал эту статью поэтому я Википедию
n’t really like Wikipedia, because in Wikipedia there
не очень люблю так в Википедии как нет в
are no links in Wikipedia,
Википедии как раз ссылочки есть вы
you just don’t have any links
просто какую-то вы не вки нете просто
Wikipedia has a whole editorial
Википедию там целый редакторский
team there to block this edit. Well,
коллектив вам заблочить эту правку Ну
go to Wikipedia, you can’t, but
Зайдите вот Википедии не Можно же
here this source refers to the KBU website and
тут это источник ссылается на сайт кбу и
we’re looking at it, let’s just say
мы смотрим это давайте скажу просто
one thing that I don’t like to communicate with
такую вещь что я не люблю общаться с
dry facts. This is like who has the
сухими фактами Вот это типа у кого язык
longest tongue I like to communicate  at the level of
длиньше Мне нравится общаться на уровне
logic, it’s simply not not Wait, stop stop,
логики просто не не Подожди стоп-стоп
logic must operate with facts and not with
логика должна оперировать фактами А не
fiction, that is, we have facts and from
вымыслом то есть у нас есть факты и из
them we make a logical chain if
них мы делаем логическую цепочку если у
we have  there are no facts, you understand, the dialogue will be
нас нет фактов понимаете диалог будет
uninteresting if we exchange.
неинтересны если мы будем обмениваться
Moreover, I don’t have the opportunity to
Тем более у меня нет возможности вам
show you screenshots here,
скрины тут показывать
I can. The fact is that if you don’t
я могу Дело в том что если не
operate with facts, you can say
оперировать фактами можно утверждать что
anything. For example, you can say that,
угодно Например можно говорить Что
for example,
например
in the Soviet Union, Yes, fewer
в Советском Союзе Да погибло меньше
people died than, for example,
людей чем например
in the Republic  there is the Congo in the Second World
в Республике там Конго во Второй мировой
War. Well, for example, I can refer. There
войне Ну например я могу ссылаться Вот
is such a person who you see. I can
есть такой человек который видите я могу
also refer to the KBU website and so on.
тоже ссылаться на сайт кбу и так дальше
You Duma, let’s do it after all.
Вы Дума давайте мы всё-таки
Don’t let us finish off. Wait, let
Не давайте мы добьём Подождите давайте
’s finish off the question.  with the French This is a very
мы добьём вопро с французами Это очень
important question because for us to
важный вопрос потому что чтобы мы
understand, either you made it up or
всё-таки поняли или это вы выдумали или
you read it on some Pikabu site,
это вы вычитали на каком-то сайте Пикабу
I don’t know what kind of sites there are, or
я не знаю какие там сайты да Или это
is it really like that? Where can we
есть реально такое Где мы можем
find it? So, here’s an article for you  said I do
найти Так ну вот я вам статью сказал я
n’t know, she refers to some
вот не знаю она ссылается на какие-то
surnames, but these surnames also need to be
фамилии Но эти фамилии тоже надо
checked, the French historian
проверять вот французский историк
Jean-François
жан-франсуа
Racho, no, this is this, let’s get some
рачо нене это это вот Давайте какой-то
real, not just that Socrates said
на реальный не просто что Сократ говорил
that not Well, you  tell me, type in here you have
что не Ну Вы скажите вбейте вот у вас
Google, type in the historian Jean Francois
Google есть вбейте историк Жан Франсуа
Moura please about the losses of France like this,
мура чтоль про потери Франции вот так
somehow, you can get
вот как-нибудь забейте вам может выдать
something there history can give you Jean
там что-то историю может выдать Жан
Francois of the world
Франсуа мира
who is the world chol n Francois Moura chch Ol
кто мира чоль н Франсуа мура чч Оль
so zagu historian Jean-Francois  Ral about the
так загу историк жан-франсуа Раль про
sweat of
потели
France and so in Wikipedia there is Jean
Франции так вот в Википедии есть Жан
Francois Champollion the war passed through the French army
Франсуа шампольон войны через армию
1350 stop stop stop  Where where are you
1350 стоп стоп стоп Где где вы это
reading this on what
читаете на каком
site is Nasaf
сайте вот насаф
maybe the only thing found on the site is
может единственное нашло на сайте
some military forum Military Review is
какой-то воен форум Военное обозрение
just there by the way, the French historian VN
просто там кстати французский историк ВН
Rahl evaluates And that’s it And nowhere else is
Раль оценивает И всё И больше нигде про
there anything about this Rahl on the
этого раля вообще нет в
Internet at all Look, I’m just driving
интернете Вот смотри я просто вожу
Jean-Francois
жан-франсуа
Mura and stupidly doesn’t find
мура и тупо не находит вообще
anything like this at all But the American Wikipedia is there,
такого А вот американская Википедия есть
I just
я вот
typed Pete in English
набрал Пит на английском языке
French resistance American
французское сопротивление американское
now look here I am again I’m in
сейчас вот смотри вот я ещё раз я на
Russian  language of the sacred Russian language
русском языке священном русском языке
Rusov yes Jean France Rahl yes about him all
Русов да Жан Франс Раль да про него всё
that is there are some
что есть это некоторые вот такие
like this in left-wing
какие-то в левых
articles on this on the live journal yes
статьях на это на живом журнале да
Jean retells this phrase that
пересказывает Жан вот эта фраза которую
you said, that is, somewhere someone
вы сказали то есть где-то кто-то скинул
immediately posted about  this guy yes without
сразу про этого чля да без подтверждения
any confirmation Yes And then he finds chips No it’s
какого-то Да И вот находит фишки Нет это
like Pikabu
типа как у Пикабу
yes yes but you can at least just
да да но вы можете хотя бы просто вот
read the American Wikipedia wait
почитать американскую Википедию подожди
oh on the site I cried there is Well I  Well,
о на сайте я плакал есть вот Ну я же
let me explain, there is a French resistance.
объясняю есть французское сопротивление
American Wikipedia has a lot
американская Википедия там очень много
written there. Come on. So we can somewhere in
написано Давайте Так мы можем где-то в
Russian sources. I think that
российских источни Я думаю что
your Russian historians, your
российские ваши историки ваши там
journalists there, have long ago moved this
журналисты уже давно вы переместили эту
somewhere on your official points to
де где-то на официальных ваших точках
read about this mural.
про этого мурале почитать
I don’t know.  you need to look for it I
Я не знаю это вам искать надо мне то
mean I I understood correctly yes What about the
есть я я я правильно понял да Что про
trick that more French people died uh in the
фишку что французов больше погибло ээ в
fight for Hitler than against Hitler all
борьбе за Гитлера чем против Гитлера всё
that is in your information
что есть в вашем информационном
space is  some kind of reference to a
пространстве это какая-то отсылка на
phrase of some
фразу какого-то
murych
мурыч
m here’s also
м вот ещё а
Anna
Анна
Marley it was written in the anthem
Марли она была написано в гимне движение
resistance movement So there’s a book it’s
сопротивления Вот и есть книга у неё
called song Partizan an art
называется песня Партизан художественная
book Well, essentially it’s like a Memoir, I think, well,
книга Ну по сути это как Мемуары я думаю
it’s a Memoir so Well, it’s not  I didn’t
ну это Мемуары так Ну она же не не
appreciate it, well, just like you in
оценивала это ну как как вы по мемуарам
your memoirs. You think I’m thinking of something in general,
своим Вот вы что-то себе считаю вообще
this is fiction, all right
это му художественная литература всё
now I’ll connect the voice assistant,
сейчас я голосовой помощник
maybe she  will find Yes Try it
подключу може она найдёт Да Попробуйте
there yes We have a holo assistant Yes
там это да У нас есть голо помощник Да
through state aid since we can’t find it with Google
через госо помощ раз мы Гуглом не можем
yes it’s the same You see That’s why I
да этоже Видите Я поэтому и вот это вот
don’t like throwing these facts
не люблю вот этими фактами закидываться
at me Ravi names at the level of logic generally
ам мне Рави имен на уровне логики обща
trying to prove my point of view with what
пытаться доказать свою точку зрения чем
here is every word there, find the original
вот каждое слово там находить оригинал
scan of the document there But this is some kind of nonsense, I
там скана документа Но это бред какой-то
don’t know Well, or maybe you
не знаю Ну или может быть Вам это
like it, it’s not very easy for me now I’m
нравится мне не очень просто
interested, damn it, now I’ll download
сечас интересно да блин сейчас я скачаю
this voice assistant
этот голосовой помощник
Yes
Да
Oh, even here Big statistics I am a
Ой вот тут даже вот Большая статистика я
voice assistant Downloaded from us Ivanka,
голосовой помощник Скачал у нас Иванка
please tell me, my interlocutor
скажи пожалуйста вот у меня собеседник
says that the French who fought for
говорит что французы которые воевали за
Hitler killed more of them than those who
Гитлера больше их полегло чем те которые
fought against Hitler, can you please
воевали против Гитлера можешь пожалуйста
tell me in which source this was said
сказать в каком источнике такое сказано
and whether this happened I answer as  writes on the
и было ли такое отвечаю как пишет на
Pikabu website it’s just that your
сайте Пикабу это просто что твой
interlocutor is just a ba who doesn’t need
собеседник просто ба которому не нужны
facts, it’s Kolya who believes in
факты это Колу который верит в
fairy tales Well, I understand what you’ve been writing all this
сказки Ну я понял что-ты писал всё это
time, look at the statistics  I
время смотри я статистику нашёл
also found an unteachable
ещё стати необучаемый
big statistic, uh, but it’s
большая статистика вот есть э но она
also not here, there’s no such direct confirmation of
тоже тут нет такого прямо подтверждения
some kind. It’s just published, it’s also
какого-то Оно просто опубликована тоже
unclear, but the same thing
непонятно но тут тоже самое
is said here. So I don’t know, these are dry
говорится Так что я не знаю это сухие
facts. I don’t know. If you want, then
факты Я не знаю ты если захочешь потом
we’ll dive into the textbooks and find it.
погрузимся в учебники и найдёшь
the truth is that the
правду всё
cat and I all look at you like
мы с котом смотрим на тебя как
yes, that’s normal. I’m not offended at
на да это нормально Я не обижаюсь
all. I’m looking at you too. Although it’s
абсолютно я на тебя также смотрю Хотя по
not obvious to me, yes. Well, you see, I have both
мне не видно да Ну видишь у меня есть и
Facts and logic. And you  not a person, I’ll really
Факты и логика А у тебя не чел я реально
say You really, this is not a problem in life,
скажу Ты реально это не проблема в жизни
but Listen, I think it’s time for you
но Слушай мне кажется тебе пора
How do people with such a level of intelligence
Як люди с таким ривнем интеллекту
live up to this Vika tse It’s just
доживают до такого Вику це Просто просто
tough I don’t have the facts, I’m here Just by
жесть Мне нете факты я вот Просто по
logic Yes, by logic you can say yes there are
логике Да по логике можно сказать да
more French in short That  there you
французов больше короче То есть ты
say a fictitious fact of the French,
говоришь вымышленный факт французов
more people fell for Hitler than against
больше легло за Гитлера чем против
Hitler and beyond. Of course, from this you
Гитлера да и дальше Конечно от этого
can use whatever logic you want when
можно логику какую хочешь крутить когда
you do what’s black, say white, and
ты делаешь на Чёрное говоришь белое и
then look at this  Well the same
Дальше смотри вот это ж одинаковое
means this is also a white letter on the Telegram
значит это тоже белое пись на й Telegram
directly at the same time he
прямо зараз он
apok tse more and more respectfully YouTube keeping
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us busy through skarg Orcs in your ban and even
нас через скарг Орки в твый бан и дуже
more videos I don’t show people at the moment I don’t
багато видео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about ST for that, for that,
показуе информация про СТ тому для того
Mali operational link to write
щоб ми Мали оперативный звязок пишиться
right now and while there in telegra okm video
прямо зараз а пок там в телегра окм вдео
information and we are
ще теж цикава и корисна информация и ми
responsible for you trimati postiyny
повинни з вами тримати постийний
operational connection
оперативный звязок
nezalezhno in that chi show you the process
незалежно в того чи покаже вам проце
YouTube Glory to Ukraine letter
YouTube Слава Украине пись
with
с